A Guide to the Caroline Holt Flemings Letters, 1846-1891
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Caroline Holt Flemings Letters, 1846-1891
The Library of Virginia
50295, 53977
.70 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Flemings, Caroline Holt
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eleanor Flemings Munch on 20 January 2012 [Acc. 50295].
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. William Munch on 8 September 2023 [Acc. 53977].
Biographical Information
Caroline Charlotte Holt was born in Andover, Massachusetts on 4 May 1826. She was the daughter of Jonas Holt (1800-1869) and Pamelia Porter Frye Holt (1806-1868). She married James Whitney Flemings (1825-1880) on 25 December 1849, and they resided in North Tewksbury, Massachusetts. Caroline Holt Flemings died on 6 October 1902.
Her brother, Warren Eugene Holt, was born on 17 April 1833. He enlisted on 5 July 1861 in Andover, Massachusetts, and was mustered into the 14th Massachusetts Infantry, which was later reorganized as the 1st Massachusetts Heavy Artillery regiment. Warren Holt married Susan Stevens (1839-1912). He died on 8 April 1884, and is buried in Spring Grove Cemetery in Andover.
Another brother, Lewis Garrison Holt, was born on 15 November 1839. He also served with the 1st Massachusetts Heavy Artillery regiment during the Civil War, and was wounded at Cold Harbor. He married Emma A. Jenkins. After the war, he lived in Lawrence, Massachusetts, where he was general manager of the Lawrence Ice Company, and also served as assessor, overseer of the poor, and selectman for Andover, and also on city council and as postmaster in Lawrence. Lewis G. Holt died in Lawrence on 23 December 1916.
Emily Parsons (1826-1890) was married to Jeremiah Coney (1806-1888) and lived in Lynnfield, Essex County, Massachusetts.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1846-1891, to Caroline Holt Flemings (1826-1902) in North Tewksbury, Middlesex County, Massachusetts. Series I includes letters, 1861-1891, from her brothers, Lewis Garrison Holt (1839-1916) and Warren Eugene Holt (1833-1884), while they were serving with the 1st Massachusetts Heavy Artillery during the Civil War. Series II includes letters, 1846-1864, to Caroline Holt Flemings from her friend, Emily Parsons Coney, written from New Hampshire and Massachusetts.
The collection was scanned as part of the James I Robertson Civil War Sesquicentennial Legacy Collection (www.virginiamemory.com/cw150) and is available online. [Search = Caroline Holt Flemings]
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Letters from Lewis Garrison Holt and Warren Eugene Holt to Caroline Holt Flemings, 1861-1891 [Acc. 50295]
Series II: Letters from Emily Parsons Coney to Caroline Holt Flemings, 1846-1864 [Acc. 53977]
Contents List
- Series I: Caroline Holt Flemings letters, 1861-1891 [Acc. 50295]., Extent: .35 cu. ft. [1 box].
  Letters, 1861-1866, 1891, to Caroline Holt Flemings (1826-1902) in North Tewksbury, Middlesex County, Massachusetts from her brothers, Lewis Garrison Holt (1839-1916) and Warren Eugene Holt (1833-1884), while they were serving with the 1st Massachusetts Heavy Artillery during the Civil War. Most of the letters were written while the regiment was stationed at Fort Albany (Va.), Fort Richardson (Va.), and Maryland Heights (Md.). Subjects include rations, weather, camp life, descriptions of living quarters and construction of buildings, troop movements and positions, brigade reviews, attending prayer meetings, troop morale and progress of the war, trips to Washington, D.C. and Alexandria, and skirmishes with the Confederate forces around Harper's Ferry. In the 1891 letter, Lewis Holt writes about the flashbacks to the war which he experienced. Also includes flyer, 2 August 1866, for a concert for the benefit of the Soldiers' and Sailors' National Orphans' Home Fund.
  The collection also includes typed transcriptions of the letters prepared by Eleanor Flemings Munch, as well as family information, and copies of service records and maps. Also includes print out of slides from presentations about the family papers given by William (Bill) Munch in 2018-2019.
  - Letters, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1862 January-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1862 June-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Flyer, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Transcriptions (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Presentations [William (Bill) Munch], 2018-2019 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Caroline Holt Flemings letters, 1846-1864., Extent: .35 cu. ft. [1 box].
  Letters, 1846-1864, to Caroline Holt Flemings (1826-1902) in North Tewksbury, Middlesex County, Massachusetts from her friend, Emily Parsons Coney (1826-1890), while in Chelsea and Lynnfield, Massachusetts, and New Hampshire. Topics include teaching, family and friends, marriage and children, health and sickness, family members serving in the Civil War, politics, and other topics. The collection also includes transcriptions of the letters along with genealogical information, transcribed and prepared by Eleanor Flemings Munch.
  - Letters, 1846-1849 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1850-1856 February (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1856 August-December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1860-1861 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1862-1864 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transcriptions (Box 2, Folder 9)